Lafayette mss., 1572-1939 LMC 2326
Lilly Library
- Manuscripts
  - Chronological
    - Richard Varrick, Speaker - Pay warrant to Morris Graham for attendance at the New York Assembly as a member from Dutchess County, 1788, March 22; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Colonel Balcames (?) - Certifying that ensign John Campbell has always served like a load officer, 1788, April 25; ADS (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Washington to Lafayette - A six page newsy letter - Refers to Great Britain's "Paper Money Bubble", 1788, April 28; Photostat 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - John Hancock and John Avery - Notice to Cotton Tufts that he has been chosen as a Senator in Suffolk, 1788, May 12; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Col. Udny Hay to Gerard Bancker - On the belated pay due the members of the New York Legislature, 1788, May 4; ADS (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Washington to Lafayette - Introducing Joel Barlow the writer, and giving him a very high compliment, 1788, May 28; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Richard Potts - Receipt to Continental Loan Officer of Maryland for interest on Certificates of Liquidated Debt, 1788, June 4; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - James Morris to "Sir", 1788, June 9; ADS (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Washington to Lafayette - An eight page letter - "Bloody work in the North of Europe", 1788, June 18; Photostat 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Edmond Pendleton, President to the Governor of New Jersey - Official notification that Virginia has ratified the Constitution - encloses copies of the "Amendments they wish to take place therein", 1788, June 28; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Includes photocopy
    - General Henry Knox to General St. Clair - A confidential letter on the discussions taking place in the various States on the ratifications of the Constitution, 1788, July 3; ADS (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - P. Wingate to Miss Hannah - "I know that you are very much of a libertine lady and don't wonder that you are tickled up with the new Constitution...they are soon to celebrate its adoption by a pompous parade and I hope it is the last I shall ever see or hear of it", 1788, July 21; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - William Malcom, Vice President to Alexander Robertson, Treasurer of St. Andrews Society - Order for payment to Collin Williamson, 1788, August 20; ADS (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - George Mason (son of George Mason, friend and neighbor of Washington) to Mathew Carey, 1788, August 30; ADS (Box 2, Folder 21)
      "George Mason? - I bought this letter at a sale at the Anderson Galleries. It was listed as "George Mason, member of the Continental Congress." On the address side there is a notation "George Mason," but I noticed that after the signature in the letter, there was some mark partly covered by the sealing wax. I have taken all the care possible to see that there are no misdescriptions in my collection and when I discovered that the signature differs from the facsimile in Appleton, I had the question taken up with the New York Public Library. My letter was compared with those in the Emmet Collection. It seems that there were five George Masons in succession. The fourth George was the neighbor and intimate friend of George Washington. The handwriting in my letter is almost identical with a fourth George's letter in the Emmet Collection, but I found there a letter of the fifth George, which indicates that my letter was signed by the son, the fifth George. The father was still alive at that time."
    - Receipt for $616.35 signed by Johnathan Trumbull II, 1788, October 7; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Lafayette to Laqueville (?) - On the Convocation of the States General, 1788, October 10; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
      "NOTE - The date and the name of the addressee were written in lead pencil on this letter at hte time it came into my possession. Judging from the text, the date may be about right."
    - James Clinton (General), John Cantine and John Hathorn (M.C.) - as Commissioners they have laid out for John Dolson, 430 acres in Town of Chemung (N.Y.), 1788, November 1; ADS (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Jean de Neufville to "Sir", 1788, November 1; ADS (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Lord Cornwallis - official appointment of Major Russel (parchment), 1788, November 1 (Ovflat 30)
    - William Duer to Benjamin Walker, Commissioner for Hospital Department - Introducing William Symington, 1788, November 12; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - C. W. Cornwall, Speaker, to the Sheriffs of the City of Chester - Official summons to the "representatives of your City to appear before the House of Commons", 1788, November 20; ADS (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Washington to Lafayette - Telling of the journeys in the States being taken by the French Minister and his family, 1788, November 27; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Versailles taxation, 1788, December 27 (Ovflat 30)
    - Wade Hampton to Seaborn Jones, Esq. (?), 1788, December 31; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Washington to Lafayette - A sincere expression of his honest reluctance to be President, 1789, January 29; Photostat 5 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Tench Coxe to John Nicholson, at Philadelphia - Settlement of the pay due soldiers, 1789, January 31; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Tristram Dalton to Alex Hodgdon, Treasurer of Mass. - Assignment of money due him as Senator, 1789, January 31; ADS (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - James Warren - Receipt for pay as Speaker of the Mass. House, 1789, February 2; ADS (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - David Sewall to George Thatcher - Giving his views of some of the questions likely to be discussed in the First Congress, 1789, February 27; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Labroue, Chasseurs de Lorraine, 1789-04-02 (Ovflat 30)
    - James Morris (nephew of Gouverneur Morris) to Ruellan and Co. (?), 1789, April 6; ADS (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Le Mal de Segur to M. de Villiers, Inspecteur de la Manufacture d'Armes a Mauberge, 1789, May 15; ADS (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Lt. Col. Charles Lennox to Lord Strathaven - Approved by Henry Fletcher, 1789, June 15; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette - His thanks for being put at head of Paris Militia and his promise to prevent disorder in the City, 1789, July 18; Photostat 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Charles Pinckney, Governor, to Gov. George Walton of Georgia - On an extradition case, 1789, July 20; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette's resignation to the National Guard of Paris as Commanding General because he is distressed that the situation has gotten out of hand, 1789, July 23; ADS (Box 2, Folder 22)
      "NOTE - THis communication was addressed to Lafayette's associates the day after the brutal murder of M. Foullon, which he had been unable to prevent. The mob would not listen to his appeal and hanged from a lamp post this seventy four year old ex-minister and ex-soldier, then cut off his head, stuffed a wisp of hay between the teeth, stuck the head on a pike and joyously paraded the streets dragging the naked body over the stones. Aghast at the horrors of that day, Lafayette resigned, saying 'the people have not listened to my advice and the day in which the confidence that they promised is wanting, I must, as I said in advance, quit a post in which I can no longer be useful."
    - Lafayette signs a Military Order, 1789, August 13; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette orders the Commander of Saint Phillipe to collect as many men as possible at the gate and prevent all troops from passing, under any pretext, 1789, August 30; ADS (Box 2, Folder 22)
      "NOTE - Dr. Gottschalk, of the University of Chicago, says of this letter: 'It shows that Lafayette did take steps to stop a march to Versailles on August 30th, though he did not do so on October 5th. Dr. Guthling in his book on Lafayette and the March to Versailles on October 5th, argues that Lafayette could have stopped them but did not want to do so. In my review of Guthling's book I said that Lafayette had no authority and did not wish to act without it. Judging from this letter it appears that he acted this time without authority, thus giving some support to Guthling's thesis."
    - James Sullivan to Elbridge Gerry - "I am convinced for myself that six dollars is by no means too much for the wages of Senator and Representatives", 1789, August 30; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Official order signed by Bailly as Mayor and Lafayette as Commandant-General, 1789, September 15; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Aaron Ogden to Pierpont Edwards, 1789, October 2; ADS (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Jacques Necker - On the reduction in price of salt and the lower taxes on it, 1789, October 10; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Washington to Lafayette - Expressing the hope that the Revolution may prove happy in its consequences to a Nation in "whose fate we have so much cause to be interested", 1789, October 14; Photostat 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - John Jervis to Serres, 1789, November 6; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Philibert de Varenne - A noted student of agriculture and a philanthropist discusses the situation of the day - "To note what is going on among men who should be examples of wisdom and patriotism, one might well conclude that material things need never be considered, even such necessities as bread, wine and meat", 1789, December 17; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Daniel Roberdeau to Matthew Carcy (?), 1789, December; ADS (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Fragments (24 lines) of a letter in the handwriting of George Washington - On it there is a notation "Washington's handwriting" which was written by Jared Sparks from whose collection the item came, 1789; ADS (Box 2, Folder 22)
      "This fragment was at first thought to be a portion of one of President Washington's Messages, but it is the opinion of the experts in the Library of Congress that it is a portion of a private letter written by the President about 1789."
      Includes correspondence between Gardner and LoC
    - Lafayette - On a letter headed "Etat Major General" - advises the Committee of the former French Guards of the names of his Aides-de-Camp who are entitled to receive the patriotic medal at the hands of the Committee. His list includes thirteen names, 1790, January 29; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Thomas Cadwalader to John Todd, Esq., 1790, February 8; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Admiral Hyde Parker to "Sir", 1790, February 28; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - William VI, Prince of Orange - signature, 1790; ADS (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Memorandum on behalf of Baron de la Coutelle - Carries a notation by Lafayette that he has known for a long time the misfortunes of this interesting family, 1790, March 11; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Peter R. Livingston to N. Lawrence, Esq., 1790, March 24; ADS (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - de la Forest to James Madison - Introducing Dr. Vacher, who had served the United States in the Revolution, 1790, April 2; ADS (Box 2, Folder 23)
      "Antoine Rene Charles Mathurin de la Forest (1756-1846) came to America in 1778 in the French Legation. After service as Vice Consul at Savannah, Philadelphia and New York, he became Consul General in 1785, returning to France in 1792 and again became Consul General in America in 1794. In 1800 he was the Minister of the Congress of Luneville, 1803-1806, Minister to Berlin and from 1808 to 1813, Minister to Spain. De la Forest was made a Peer of France in 1818 and Minister of State in 1825. Dr. John Francis Vacher was born in Toulon, France. Graduated as a physician and surgeon from Montepellier. Served during the Revolution of 1776 in this capacity with the 4th NY Regiment. After this he resided in NYC until his death in 1807. Buried in St. Paul's Churchyard. His daughter, Sarah, married John van Vont in Jersey City."
    - Baron von Steuben to Walker - Settling an account, 1790, May 1; ADS (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Includes notes regarding the second signature, Toussaint Lopes
    - General Henry Seymour Conway to Yonge - Disposing of commission of Wadman, 1790, June 3; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Catherine II (Catherine the Great) to vice-admiral prince of Nassau, Tzarskoe-Selo, 1790, June 10; ADS (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Edward Shippen to Jasper Yeates accounting for certain claims, 1790, June 18; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Latour Maubourg to "Comte", 1790, July 1; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Necker - He discusses a Government transaction involving 30,000,000 of assignats - "Indispensibly necessary for the expenses of a month", 1790, July 16; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Emanuel Marie Louis de Noailles (uncle of Lafayette) - Presenting Charles Frederic Louis comte de Nostitz, 1790, August 4; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Pierce Butler and Ralph Izard, the two Senators from South Carolina to the Governor of their State on the subject being discussed by Congress, namely the war claims of the various states, 1790, August 11; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Joseph Van Size, Cap. of the "James" - The papers of a "Privateer", 1790, September 14; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Francois Claude Amour, marquis de Bouille, to M. de la Tour du Pin, 1790, September 13; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Bouille was so universally despised in France that he is referenced as a hated royalist in La Marseillaise
    - "Extrait d'une lettre de l'Honorable Alexander Hamilton, secretaire de la Tresorerie des Etats-Unis au Major l'Enfant" - Signed by de la Forest, 1790, September 29; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Joseph Nourse, Register to Nathaniel Appleton, at Boston - Arrangements for the new issue of Certificates, 1790, October 12; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
      "NOTE - The address sheet is franked with the original signature of Alexander Hamilton."
    - Certified copy of the Minutes of the section of Roule in Paris - Sets forth that there has been a misunderstanding in regard to a letter from the King to Lafayette, which aroused suspicion against the latter, 1790, November 12; ADS with seal (Box 2, Folder 23)
      "The authentic letter [from the King to Lafayette] justified no such suspicion [against Lafayette]. Confidence in Lafayette is not clearly expressed and it is stated that the matter should be the subject of public debate. It declares "accustomed to confide in the loyalty and love of freedom which Monsieur Lafayette exhibited in two worlds, it will be his own responsibility, if any further suspicions arise."
    - Mirabeau (3rd person) to Mr. Clarkson - HE is now suffering with very bad eyes which keeps him at home and prevents him from riding, 1790, November 15; ADS (Box 2, Folder 23)
      "NOTE - It is likely that the above item is not in the handwriting of Mirabeau, compared with the fragment known to be in his hand that appears in this collection."
      "NOTE - I am inclined to think that the Mr. Clarkson is Thomas H. (1760-1846), an English Abolitionist who wrote "A History of Abolition of the Slave Trade" (1808). He and Lafayette were correspondents. Mirabeau was very much interested in the slavery question."
    - Major William Jackson (Private Secretary to President Washington) to Charles Lee - The President required gold coin for his accommodations on a journey to Philadelphia, 1790, November 16; ADS (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Comtesse de Rochambeau (wife of General Rochambeau and mother of his aide, Viscount Rochambeau) to General Washington - Requests that her husband's Aide, Baron Closen, be "decorated with this emblem of Liberty," i.e., membership in the Order of the Cincinnati, 1790, November 18; ADS (Box 2, Folder 23)
      "I bought this Madame Rochambeau letter because of its family flavor and did not closely study its text. Its reference to "Your Excellency" indicated that it might have been addressed to Washington, but that was only an inference. I have just been reading "With Americans of Past and Present days" by former Ambassador J. J. Jusserand, published in 1916. In it there is an article entitled "Rochambeau and the French in America - from unpublished documents," and on page 119 he says - 'The Countess de Rochambeau sometimes takes up the pen, and in one of her letters appeals to Washington in favor of dear Closen who, though he had every right to be included in it, had been forgotten when the list of the original Cincinnati had been drawn up. The request was at once granted.' Below there is an explanatory foot note and much to my surprise I find that he has quoted in full the identical text of my letter. I have written to the Ambassador telling him the story and asking him where he secured his data, sending him at the same time a photostat of the letter. His reply may throw some light on whether my letter is the identical one sent to General Washington, or a duplicate given by the Countess to Baron Closen."
    - Marquis Lansdowne - Writes on the French situation, 1790, November 25; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
      "The letters of Lord Lansdowne, William Petty, the 2nd Earl Shelburne, may be to William Roscoe, 1753-1831, historian, who was born in Liverpool and lived near there. Three of the letters mention Mrs. Roscoe, and the recipient lived in Liverpool."
    - Lafayette to General Duportail - Recommending an "old cannoner in the Regiment of Aisne," National Guard, 1790, November 30; ADS (Box 2, Folder 23)
      "Louis Lebeque Duportail (1736-1802) was one of the four French officers engaged by Franklin and SIlas Deane to serve in the American Army. He was appointed a Major General by Congress and had charge of the engineering operations at Yorktown, for which he was particularly mentioned by Washington in his despatches. Through his friendship with Lafayette, he became Minister of War under Louis XVI in 1790."
    - Lieutenant Colonel Henry Barry to William Pitt the Younger (?), 1790, December 21; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Lescuyer Daquicourt, former Captain of Dragoons, requesting a position in the National Gendarmerie - Endorsed by nine members of the Military Committee, four of whom served in America: Alexander Lameth, Noailles, Broglie, and Wimpffen, 1790, December 27; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
      "This is the request dated Dacember 27, 1790 of Lescuyer Daquicourt, formerly a captain of dragoons, for a position in the National Gendarmie. It is addressed to the MIlitary Committee of the National Assembly. He represents himself as having lost everything and existing with no resources, although he has nine children. He recites that in his very early youth he was a lieutenant in the Kings regiment, in which he had served during the War of 1757. He adds that M. de Menar will gladly place before the Committee the evidence which, the writer hopes, renders him worthy of the appreciation of the Committee. A postscript (on page 2) indicates his sympathy with the Revolution as indicated by his having accepted a position in the National Guard. On page 3 is another addition: If the Committee will not put him back as Lieutenant-Marshall, he desires to go back as a Captain of Dragoons. He earnestly pleads for this. "I am," he says, "without bread." Nine children (he has) and five of them, his sons, he has taught to love and respect the new constitution. At the foot of the document is the report, signed by nine members of the Military Committee: "Lieutenant-Marshals are regarded as disbanded in the decree which calls to duty for the positions of lieutenants of the National Gendarmie the disbanded officers."
    - Lafayette, Noailles Lafayette and de Lusignam - A bond, initialed on the first page but signed in full by all three on the second page, 1790, December 30; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Bailly to M. Rognier on the question of providing food for the prisoners in the Chantels - The state of the City's finances is not good enough to permit it to be charged with any debt except for those for which it is clearly responsible, 1791, January 4; ADS (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Statement of Gueroult Duberville, bodyguard of the King - Describing the wounds he received at Versailles - taken before and signed by Joron DMM, "Doctor of Medicine in the University of Montpellier", 1791, January 14; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Statement of Berthaud, Swiss Captain of the Ordinary Bodyguard of the King, that he had carried Gueroult within the gate of the castle, after he had been wounded - signed Paris, 1791, January 19; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Statement of Favier, Surgeon of the King for his Palace of the Tuilleries that he had treated Gueroult Duberville for his injuries and that he will probably lose the sight of one eye, 1791, January 20; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Duc de Lauzun to ? - "I am leaving for my command at the front", 1791, January 20; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Statement of the "Woman Guerin" of the linen wardrobe of the Queen, signed by her, that she had seen the effect of the attack on Gueroz (Gueroult), 1791, January 21; ADS (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Noailles Lafayette to her father Duc d'Ayen in support of the question that Geroult be given the Cross of St. Louis - She adds that she ahd given him shelter because he had been wounded severely, but he had insisted that he return to the Tuilleries, next day, 1791, January 21; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Includes bookseller's description and summary of the letter's contents
    - Charles de Lameth (fellow officer with Lafayette in America), 1791, February 6; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Includes handwritten note about contents, with biographical notes on Lameth
    - Delessart, Minister of the Interior to M. Dufrense - An allotment for the expenses of a Commission to restore order in the Department of the Gard, 1791, February 27; ADS (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Mary Clinton to her husband, James Clinton, telling him that his brother is in failing health and "thinks its hard that you and De Witt [son of James] don't write to him", 1791, March 2; ADS (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Contemporaneous written account of an interview with the King and Queen on the subject of Lafayette, 1791, April 7; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
      "The interviewer or his amanuensis has noted in the text that certain answers were written in the handwriting of the King and that one of the answers was dictated by the Queen"
    - John Tither (?) to Caesar A. Rodney, "student of law with Joseph McKean" - Regarding land, 1791, May 11; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - William Augustine Washington - Order of payment, 1791, May 15; ADS (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Confort Sage - Manifest of Sloop "William and George", 1791, May 16; ADS (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Governor Beverley Randolph - Appointment of Justices of the Peace, 1791, May 31; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Lieut. Col. Marinus Willett (served with Lafayette in Jersey Campaign) - Receipt, 1791, June 4; ADS (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Duportail, Minister of War to Alexander Lameth - Concerning two grenadiers of the Fifth Regiment and their punishment for having been held guilty of formal disobedience, 1791, June 17; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Official certificate of Amnesty - Signed by Saint Maur, des Maisons and Mulot, 1791, June 30; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Major William Croghan - Receipt for survey money for lands of John Caldwell on the "Waters of the Ohio", 1791, July 13; ADS (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Dutilh & Wachsmuth, a Philadelphia merchant company - Check for $75, 1791, July 26; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 24)